If you're increasing the energy and you're
and you're simultaneously getting people
to configure their goals and those two
things are happening at the same time,
that
should increase the probability that the
goals that they adopt will be instantiated
permanently into memory. And then it's
also not exactly the kind of memory that
you
would call to mind to talk about. It's the
kind of memory that you see the world
through. So that's a different, that's
procedural memory, it's completely
different
kind of memory. I got it.
It's the kind of memory that so let's say
you practice applying a certain framework
of interpretation to your circumstances.
Okay, that practice reconfigures
procedural
memory, and that's literally the that's
rewiring of the system through which you
view the world.
That's correct. Right, And we have a new
view of the world. You come up with new
meanings. And meanings, as you know, we
both know you do your maps of meaning. My
entire life has been, you know, I remember
reading Man's Search for Meaning. I'm
actually making the film. And it was one
of the books that influenced me the most
because the ability to find meaning, even
in the most difficult time, and Victor
Frankel to me is a just a godsend to this
planet. It's crazy. It's crazy. If you
haven't read it, please, whoever you're
listening, read Or you ever anybody's ever
replaced it.
Great.
Yes.
That book. It's incredible. But the point
of your meanings change, your focus and
your meanings change when your energy
shifts. And so it's so fundamental to
bring
that energy up. And most people have no
reference for it in their body. You know,
if
you go to a concert, I remember Pat Riley
came to one of our who you know owns a
piece of the Miami Heat, who was an
amazing coach. If you're not familiar with
the
NBA basketball, one of the winning coaches
in history, good friend of mine known him
for 30 years, and he came to one of our
programs and he said, Tony, this is like
The seventh game of the NBA championship,
but it goes on for four days and it's 13
hours a day. So that vibrancy, and most
people at the game are cheering at times
and
not, this is an experience in your body.
That's why I do the number of hours.
That's
why it's immersion. That's why it's
multiple days, four days or six days, and
that's
why it has the lasting impact. But you're
right, the dopamine circuits are actually
creating what's the white matter in your
brain? The myelin, right? Creating the
myelin.
Yeah, that's right. They think
Look at a great athlete, you know, the
like you know, people look at somebody
like
you know, I'm fortunate enough to own a
piece of several sporting teams, and one
of
them is the Golden State Warriors, and you
look at Steph Curry, the greatest
33-point shooter in the world, and people
look at him, and he goes and he shoots the
ball from like almost half court, and he's
chomping on the side of his mouthpiece,
and he doesn't even wait to go. He turns
and smiles, and he knows, and then all of
a
sudden the crowd goes wild and it goes
through. It's like it looks like
impossible.
But where did that impossible come from?
He built the myelin over and over and over
again. So it's hard work. Yeah, exactly.
He knows exactly what didn't how do he do
that? This is the part that we all forget.
I always tell people when you see people
who are amazing in public, they're being
rewarded in public for what they've
practiced massively in practice. So here's
his
plan. Just take 15 years in the NBA,
that's the only he's been there. Greatest
three-point shooter in history, nobody
even close if you're not familiar with the
NBA. He practices.
Yes,
500 shots a day, every day, seven days a
week, bar none. That's thirty five hundred
shots a week. It's a hundred and sixty-
eight thousand shots a month. Right. Two
point five two million shots, not forget
his college career, just in his
professional career, so that he can make
thirty three hundred three-point shots and
be the greatest in history. That's less
than one-tenth of one percent of the time
was it compared to his practice. Right. So
the wiring in him is so powerful, but it
doesn't just show up.
Hope and excitement are wonderful things,
but you need competency as well. And in
order to have that, the hope can get you
started, give you the drive, the vision,
the aim. But you've got to have the
execution. You have both the strategy and
you've
got to have the execution that's
practical.
Okay. So let's talk about that because you
talked about eliciting motivation over a
long period of time. So I'd like to know
more about
I even say the word, if I may, drive.
Because motivation is the reason I use it,
it's like a warm bath. You should probably
take a bath, but it doesn't last, right?
You should still do it. But drive is like
everyone is motivated. If you're
overweight, you're motivated to eat,
right? Come on. I want to find out what
drives
you because if we unleash your drives,
what is it that will unleash you? That's
what
this experience is about. That's different
than just being motivated.
Drives you towards a the right age.
Okay, so let's walk okay, so I have an
exercise that people can do online called
future authoring, and one of its steps,
and I'd like you to tell me how this
compares to what you're doing in your
seminars, in your events. So it's a
conditions
of satisfaction exercise, or it's a it's a
meditation and contemplation exercise, or
it's a prayer. You could think of all the
or a request for revelation. But here's
the here's the idea. So
It's you can you imagine for a moment that
you could have what you wanted and needed
in five years. Okay, but there's a
condition. You have to know what it is and
you
have to specify it. Okay, now the then the
question would be, well, how are you
going to discover that? And the answer is
you ask yourself. It's like, okay, like
what would it's like the Victor Frankel
scenario, even hypothetically, what would
get me out of the m bed in the morning on
a very, difficult day? Yes. Like
What could I imagine?
Yeah. Make you f fully alive.
Yeah, well what would make you persevere
in times of trouble? Okay, so and oh
By the way, I find tell me if the same for
you. Yeah. It's not just the aim or
objective, it's strong enough reasons. In
other words, somebody say, I want to make
a billion dollars, but they don't do it.
And they even envision to get excited
about
it, a million dollars, whatever it is. I
want to have three perfect children, I
want
to write a book, whatever. The secret is
reasons come first, answers come second.
Once I know what I want, I gotta figure
out why. Yes. Because purpose is stronger
than object. So the object may inspire
you, but what's gonna keep you going is
strong enough reasons when it's tough.
What are the reasons? Okay, I want this
money for what? Well, I want to provide a
home for my mom. Well, that's very
different than I just want to have this
pieces of
paper with pictures of dead people on it,
right? And people say I want money, they
don't want money. They want an emotion.
They want an impact. They want security or
they want freedom or they want to be able
to contribute or they want to do something
they think money will give them more
choices on, right? They don't want the
money.
So I'm always trying to dig underneath to
figure out what is the exactly.
That's the substructure. Yeah, okay.
The surface desire. Right. And many people
focus on the surface desire not knowing
enough reasons to follow through. That's
why New Year's resolutions don't work. 91%
of them, I know what the weight of
statistic is, people don't follow through
after
three weeks. By the time they're hearing
us speak, if they have news resolutions,
they're gone. Because they don't have the
reasons to push through and they don't
have the strategy. It's wonderful if you
say, I want to see a sunset, but if your
strategy is start running east as fast as
you can, I don't give a damn how positive
you are. It's not gonna work. Yeah, right.
So it's a combination of
That aim, those values, that drive you and
I are talking about, that ignite enough
reasons for it and then the strategies to
execute, because you'll eventually find
your way there. But the speed at which you
do it is if I believe in modeling. I
believe success leaves clues. My original
teacher, Jim Rohn, taught me that. He
said, if someone is successful at
anything, they've got a great relationship
and
it's 20 years down the line and they still
do it. Or they lost weight and kept it
off for 10, years, or they went from
nothing to
To not just making money, but sustaining
financial security and freedom for their
family. They're not lucky. They're doing
something different than you are. So
instead of you trial and trial and error,
which is the standard way in which we
learn, you find the pathway to power by
finding someone who's done it consistently
and produced results. That obsession
within me has launched most of the books
I've
written, most things I've done. It's like,
I want to know what, you know, this book
was how do I help people with.
The best breakthroughs in health, for
example, life force and energy, they take
years to go from the breakthrough time to
your clinician. Like, how do I shorten
that up? I'm gonna interview 150 of the
most brilliant regenerative doctors in the
world, Nobel Prize winners, and find out
what they're doing, give it to you right
now. Or I'm gonna finance. Well, I can
talk to you finance about what I think, or
I
can go interview 50 of the smartest
financial people in the history of the
world
that are alive today and find out.
What do they do? And while they're
different, I look for what are the common
strategies, elements, what is guiding
this? And then I can teach that my
billionaire
client goes, this is incredible, and the
average person goes, this is incredible.
Because it's about f it's very much what
you do. It's finding the pathway, it's
finding the DNA, it's finding the codex of
how to go from where you are to where you
want to be. But it is more than just the
aim that'll start you. It's you've got to
have the purpose or the reasons or your
purpose.
If it's somebody else's purpose or reason
is won't work, and then you need the
strategies too, because that'll give you
the drive. And you will figure it out if
you are you if you can discipline your
disappointment, if you can push yourself
beyond what most people give up on, you're
gonna get there eventually. You're gonna
keep flexing. But you'll get there ten
times faster if you can say, Wow, there's
already a pathway that's been proven. Why
would I reinvent the wheel? I'll still
bring myself to it, my own uniqueness to
it.
That's not gonna work.
But there's certain fundamentals that if
you do them, you're gonna have economic
abundance. If you don't, you're gonna have
pain. There's certain great
relationships. That's exactly
actually the that's the purpose of story
right okay so you said something that I
think we could delve into technically too
okay so you said an aim isn't sufficient
it'll get you started okay and then you
said you have to have reasons okay so
let's
think that through for a minute so one of
the things we do in this program that
helps people rewire their aim is do a
multidimensional analysis and we step
people
through that it's like okay now you've
sort of figured out what
you would want and need if you could have
it. But let's flesh that out so you could
say, well, how would that positively
affect your intimate relationship, your
marriage? Right? How would that positively
affect your family? How would it affect
your community?
So you're making them come up with
reasons.
Well then you can imagine this too. You
could imagine that like in some ways we're
loose connect we're loose constellations
of multiple motivations. And you want to
meld those all together so they're serving
the same aim.
supposed being pulled apart. Exactly. I
want I want to be totally successful and
never be rejected. Right. If you're gonna
be successful on a social scale, you know,
that's not possible. And so if you have
those two conflicts, you're gonna take two
steps forward and three back. And that's
what we do with people. We have them
re-engineer the values so they pull you
forward as a polls pull you apart. Yes.
Because most of us have so many conflicts.
It's a lack of clarity usually right
there's not a clear aim. There's not
enough reasons. Yeah. Poor strategy.
But ultimately what really stops people
and what I do with people in events is I
find the inner conflict. Inner conflict is
what's keeping them from executing. oh
Yes, definitely.
actually living out multiple stories
simultaneously and they don't have the
same
aim. That's right. Yeah, Okay.
It's okay too. It doesn't have to all be
the same story, but there has to be some
unifying element to what matters most to
you for you to live an extraordinary
quality of life. Again, life on your
terms. What you think is that three
children?
Is that writing a book? Is that building a
business? Is that all the above? I don't
know. Okay, so it's gotta be on your
terms.
One of the things I discovered when I was
walking through the biblical stories is
there the book itself is structured in a
manner that's analogous to the pattern
that
you just described. So what happens in the
biblical stories is that a sequence of
stories are put forward that each
circulate around a form of high order
goal. So
I'll give you an example. So in the story
of Noah, for example, the
The voice of the divine in the story of
Noah is characterized as the intuition
that
calls the wise to prepare when trouble is
brewing. Right? So that's God for Noah.
Because Noah is described as a man who's
wise in his generation. So he's the sort
of
person you'd go to for advice. And his
ability to intuit is well developed in
consequence of his practice of wisdom. And
everyone recognizes that. And now he has
a powerful revelation or intuition that
all hell's about to break loose.
And he should take appropriate steps. And
that's his faith in God. But God, in that
what the highest goal, you might say, in
that story is this intuition of the wise
to
prepare in the face of disaster. Okay.
That's very different than the God that
makes
himself manifest to Abraham. So Abraham is
someone who's resting on his laurels and
who's privileged at the beginning of the
story. His parents are wealthy, and
there's
no reason for him to lift a finger.
And he comes, God comes to him as the
voice of adventure. And God says to him,
It's
very, it's very cool. This is the
covenant, by the way. And I I'm sure
you'll see
the relationship between this and what
you're doing in your seminars. God comes
to
Moses as a spirit of adventure and he and
he offers him a bargain, which is the
covenant. He says, if you leave your zone
of comfort, if you move away from your
father's tent, if you move away from
what's familiar to you, and you do that
voluntarily.
And you make the sacrifices necessary as a
consequence, this is what will happen.
If you persist long enough 'cause it took
you he like ninety eight to have his first
kid, right? But he but he didn't give up.
He just kept moving forward. It didn't
matter if he made mistakes, he kept moving
in the right direction.
Yeah, exactly.
Yes, and that's partly the element of his
faith. Okay, so the deal is your life will
become a blessing to you. So that's that
antidepressant phenomena that we're
describing. So instead of living in
misery, you'll live in something
approximating
hope and security. Yes. Right. Okay,
that's the first part of the deal. The
second
part is your name will become renowned
among other people and you'll deserve it.
So
that's a good deal because people want
social status and they want
the security and the capacity to cooperate
and compete peacefully that goes along
with that. It's a fundamental, it might
even be the fundamental human aim, but it
it's at least a fundamental human aim.
That's number two. Number three is it'll
give
your best shot at establishing something
of multi-generational permanence. Right.
So
that's a good deal because, you know, one
of the things that people want when they
search for what's meaningful is that
They say, well, I'd like to do something
that lasts or matters. Yes, I got it.
Yeah.
Okay. So that's the third thing. And the
fourth thing is you'll do it in a way
that'll be of a benefit to everyone else.
So it's not a zero sum game. Yes. And so
what it's so cool this story, because what
it does is align the calling of
adventure. So that would be that calling
or pull with those four outcomes. Okay,
but
then there's a meta move in the
Which gives you more reasons. Because
we'll always do more we'll always do more
for
those we love than we will for ourselves.
Yes, right. That's the beauty of being
human. That's humanity at its best, right?
Yes, that's why you want to think through,
if you do have an aim, what the benefit
would be to the people that you love and
to your community. Right. Because it
anchors it. Okay. The meta claim in the
juxtaposition of these narratives, this is
so cool, is that the voice that tells the
wise to prepare in the time of crisis and
the call to adventure are manifestations
of the same distal goal. Yes. So you could
imagine that the ultimate uniting goal.
Brings all the underlying potential
stories together. Yes. And then that's
developed
through the biblical corpus. And in the
New Testament, that's fleshed out
completely
because the claim in the New Testament is
something like the embodiment of the
spirit that's characterized in multiple
ways in the Old Testament is made manifest
as the willingness for voluntary self-
sacrifice in spirit.
service of the highest goal. And that's
what's acted out in the passion story. And
that seems to me to be precisely accurate.
Is that there's that because you said
yourself earlier, you know, that a goal
that is only serving your own, so to
speak,
narrow and proximal motives isn't one
that's going to last. It has to be
anchored in
multiple ways and it has to be worthwhile.
But there is this insistence that's I
think this is the monotheistic hypothesis
actually is that the
There is a distal aim that unites all
subordinate aims. And if you can ally
yourself
with that, you become something
approximating an unstoppable force.
And that's where all the energy comes
from. Yeah. Because there's so much. I
look at
it this way. you can call it God or you
can call it life, whatever you're pre- I
prefer God, but still life supports
whatever supports more life. So what as an
individual with my own goals, take your
bees, the bumblebee could be selfishly
going
after just the nectar for itself, if you
want to call that selfish, but then
What attaches to its legs is pollen,
that's why more flowers, right? So there's
a
certain amount of benefit by anyone's
individual desires, desire of the father,
right? You know, it's like with that
desire is the ability to fulfill it if you
can
persist and discover. But I found that I
believe that when your desire is to serve
something more than yourself, first of
all, you get out of yourself. So there's
no
more of the internal anxieties if you're
sure you're not there.
Well those are I d you know that concern
thoughts of yourself and neurotic
suffering
are so closely allied statistically that
you can't separate them. So if you're
thinking about your narrow self, that's
the definition of misery.
Yes, that's a great